Guide to the Elsie P. Johnston Collection 1940-1989
Montana Historical Society
Elsie P. Johnston collection
1940-1989
Montana Historical Society Research Center Archives 225 N. Roberts PO Box 201201 Helena MT 59620-1201 (406) 444-2681 MHSlibrary@mt.gov
MC 456
Johnston, Elsie P.
0.2 linear feet
This collection contains materials related to and gathered by Elsie P. Johnston regarding Montana music and the Montana music programs created by Johnston. Materials include general correspondence, sheet music, musical lyrics, programs, photographs, speeches, and newspaper clippings. Dates range from 1940 to 1989.
Historical Note
Elsie P. Johnson was born in 1902 in Fromberg, Montana, daughter of Joseph and Mary (Jedlicka) Pokarney. She attended Dillon Normal College and later taught at Cherry Springs school. In 1924, she married Paul Alfred Johnston in Sheridan, Wyoming and in 1932, the couple moved to Laurel, Montana, where Elsie became a member of the Laurel Methodist Church, the Order of Eastern Star, and the Laurel Women’s Club. She became interested in Montana music after being assigned by the Laurel Women’s Club to look into the history of Montana music for the club’s yearbook. Johnston reached out to the Library of Congress and the Montana Historical Society in search of songs and music about Montana or written by Montana residents. Songs she gathered included “Beautiful Montana,” by A. H. Boucher, “Montana,” (the Montana state song) by Joseph Howard, “The Mountain State” by Frank L. and Minnie Kern, and many others. In addition to collecting Montana music, Johnston also sang in a woman’s group and organized historical music programs that performed Montana songs and provided information on their creators and history. Johnston died in 1997 at the age of 94.
This collection contains materials relating to and gathered by Elsie P. Johnston regarding Montana music and the Montana music programs. Materials include general correspondence between Johnston and various Montana song writers, librarians at the Library of Congress, staff at the Montana Historical Society (including William Lang and Lucinda Scott), and others. The collection also includes Montana music lyrics, sheet music, programs where Johnston or others performed, as well as photographs, speeches, and newspaper clippings. Dates of the materials range from 1940 to 1989.
This collection is arranged into 5 series: 1) General Correspondence, 2) Montana Music, 3) Programs, 4) Speeches, and 5) Clippings.
Collection is open for research.
Acquisition information available upon request.
This collection is indexed under the following headings in the Montana Historical Society Research Center catalog. Researchers desiring materials about related topics, persons, or places should search under these terms.
Johnston, Elsie P.
Composers -- Montana
Lyricists -- Montana
Music -- Montana
Music -- Performance
Singing
State Songs -- Montana
Montana
Montana
Detailed Description of the Collection
- General Correspondence
  - A-C (Helen Ann Aaberg, Lonne Bell, A. H. Boucher, Mrs. Cooke, Clarence E. Cunningham), 1940-1985 (Box-folder 1 / 1)
  - D-F (Marjorie Dunstan, Eleanor Fiock, Grace Flugstad, Mead Butler Flugstad), 1946-1980 (Box-folder 1 / 2)
  - G-H (Edna Gerry, Mrs. B. Handenbrook, Edna Hall, LeGrande Harvery, Frederic J. Haskin), 1943-1983 (Box-folder 1 / 3)
  - J-K (Harry Johnson, Jeanette Johnson, Mrs. A. Johnson, Melvin Knoyle, Mrs. E. Kramer), 1946-1979 (Box-folder 1 / 4)
  - L (William L. Lang), 1985-1986 (Box-folder 1 / 5)
  - M (Jon M., Helen McDonald, Eva H. McEwen, Dale R. McEwen), 1946-1982 (Box-folder 1 / 6)
  - N-R (William Nokes, Mrs. Rod Paisley, Helen Rouns, Della Roll), 1946-1977 (Box-folder 1 / 7)
  - S-Z (Lucinda B. Scott, Mrs. Sommers, Louise Sletten, Lillian Seymour), 1946-1970 (Box-folder 1 / 8)
- Montana Music
  - List of Montana Songs, undated (Box-folder 1 / 9)
  - "Beautiful Montana: Where the Bittersweet Flowers Grow," words and music by A. H. Boucher, circa 1914-1945 (Box-folder 1 / 10)
  - "Beneath Montana Skies," words by Melvin Knoyle and music by Bill Nokes, circa 1947 (Box-folder 1 / 11)
  - "El Grito," words by Victory Sullivan, 1950 (Box-folder 1 / 12)
  - "I Long For The Wide Open Spaces," words by Marguerite Lysne and music by Elnor O. Overland, 1947 (Box-folder 1 / 13)
  - "Joggin' Along," words by Friend Curtis and music by Elnor. O. Overland, undated (Box-folder 1 / 14)
  - "L'Ensemble," words and music by Harry S. Mecartney, 1917 (Box-folder 1 / 15)
  - "Montana Great and Grand," words by H. M. Butler and Mead Butler Flugstad and music by Frank S. Wildt, 1974 (Box-folder 1 / 16)
  - "Montana Melody," words and music by LeGrande Harvey and Charlene Harvey, circa 1983 (Box-folder 1 / 17)
  - "Montana," words by Charles C. Cohan and music by Joseph E. Howard (Montana State Song), 1938-1988 (Box-folder 1 / 18)
  - "The Mountain State," words and music by Frank L. Kern and Minnie C. Kern, 1896 (Box-folder 1 / 19)
  - "We Love Our Own Montana," words and music by Nona Alice Weiser, 1936-1946 (Box-folder 1 / 20)
  - "Wind in the Sage," words by Marguerite Lysne and music by Elnor O.Overland, undated (Box-folder 1 / 21)
  - Miscellaneous Music ("Mary Montana," "A Ride," "Our Uncle State Montana," "In Montana," "East Meets West," "My Home's in Montana," "Montana Wonderland,"), undated (Box-folder 1 / 22)
- Programs
  - Booklet of Montana Music and Programs, circa 1980 (Box-folder 1 / 23)
  - List of Montana Music Presentations, undated (Box-folder 1 / 24)
  - Montana Music Programs, 1941-1948 (Box-folder 1 / 25)
  - Montana Music Programs, 1961-1964 (Box-folder 1 / 26)
  - Montana Music Programs, 1972-1978 (Box-folder 1 / 27)
  - Photographs of Singers in Centennial Costume, 1977 (Box-folder 1 / 28)
  - Montana Music Programs, 1984-1989 (Box-folder 1 / 29)
  - Montana Music Programs, undated (Box-folder 1 / 30)
- Speeches
  - Miscellaneous Speeches, undated (Box-folder 1 / 31)
- Clippings
  - Newspaper clippings, circa 1940-1989 (Box-folder 1 / 32)